It is truly unfortunate that our tentative response to the UK breaking away from the EU
through Brexit is to consider a defensive European community.
This fear of the other, this preparation for war as a common link between the European people
is absurd.
We built this Europe for peace, and we are now told that we must prepare for war.
Indeed, this is what is at stake today:
if we arm ourselves, if we organize
in order to be armed together without designating any single adversary,
it means that we are seeing the entire world as a potential enemy.
"Defence", you say, but against whom? That, you do not specify.
As we all know, there is no common European policy when it comes to foreign affairs.
Thus, we are now back to the origins of the European community, since the first plan
that was proposed to the European people in 1954 was the European Defence Community.
To that, my country said "no", just as we would say "no" today if we were asked.
In reality, this is about a division of roles between the USA and Europe,
the USA turning to Asia while we would be relegated to
being put into the hands of any provocation coming from Ukraine.
Mister President, I only have one last thing to say:
France has a defence system that is not compatible with this way of allocating roles.
It requires our independence and the use of deterrence.
No war! No war! But peace!